so I've got a suitor here I've
translated it if it's quite different
from the other just sort of standard
translations it might raise some
interesting points so on occasion the
Buddha was living someone's available
who died he approaches the butter and
says this it is marvellous mantain it is
wonderful bunting ante how much has been
done by me and the extent of my respect
and my shame and fear of wrongdoing but
that's a different translation and I
think the standard one is like something
like how helpful respect actually I
think literally it's he's saying how
much has been done by me
so yeah so he's sort of commenting on
how far he's come he says I wasn't doing
much with the Dumber I wasn't doing much
with the Sangha I wasn't like
particularly engaged with the Dhamma
engaging the Sangha but seeing my love
for the Buddha and respect and shame and
fair wrongdoing
I went forth from home to homelessness
who's just mean it's fine
exactly I think payment inspiration
devotion so it's often like a negative
yeah love completely base many villains
yeah yeah effect so yes they're seeing
my love the auspicious want to respect
the shame and fear wrongdoing
I went forth from hometown business the
Buddha taught me the Dhamma
such as matter such as the arising of
matter such as the disappearing of
matter such as feeling perception
determination as consciousness such as
the arising of consciousness such as the
disappearing of consciousness Bonsang
having gone forth to an empty dwelling
pondering over turning round the upside
down this of the five assumed aggregates
I've discerned the essence of this is
suffering I discerned the
so this is the arising of suffering this
is the cessation of suffering but
discerning the right order he discerned
the Four Noble Truths so you might maybe
to say about the Pali of that because
you might sound as if because we keep
talking about the right over there yeah
it might sound as if the translation
tries to read into the suit down yes
what we wanted to say exactly I can
imagine folks if you look at the Paladin
where does the person so the normal
translation for this I should say so
Nepali is good job kujah and Baba Kuja
together as a compound and so in the
commentary it takes that to mean so
cuckoo Jia is rise and avocado has fall
and it says something like it's the
arising is called surge a Kuja and the
fall is declined
thus he was exploring the aggregates by
way of rise and fall you see there's
only the problem with that how can you
explore what you are were the basis of
your sense of self is how can you see
that decline surge unless you seen
yourself separate from it so you can
look at it like when your own eye is
subjected to rise a fall if you want to
take that to mean that how can you see
that mean I can only see the sights how
can I have a sight of itself that's
impossible so how can then I understand the nature
so how can then I understand the nature
of itself if it merely knows how to
approach it through sights
he can't nature is is is unattainable
and understanding what is unattainable
if if all your I can do is see if
there's no knowledge in regard to the
eye yeah
and that whole description of the search
default always ties in with the view of
I just have to keep observing things
changing observing things changing it's
still about observation that's the
observer elements completely unknown but
there are you can see that there are
places in the suitors way on the level
of endurance when we discussed before
even that it's not on the level of
observation well no seeing it is is
seeing seeing so so I've got so
bodhisattva passing yeah he'd well
dwells as one who sees rising this
Sunday and what sees me he dies no no no
sees well that's not so but they're
rising and falling in the five assumed
aggregates this is massive this is
rising this is disappearing so you see
matter you see it's again again let's
not conflate the two yeah what I was
saying is seeing with the eyes the view
is always where you just have to observe
the change in the aggregates now you're
using what seeing in the center like oh
I saw the truth yeah exactly
I'm referring to the actual scene
literal seeing with your eyes so none of
that applies and the Buddha we passed
was exactly that he understood the
nature of the five aggregates before he
became the Buddha yeah and then observed
that with right view yeah of course what
cause that's what drive view is then he
observed that or he was seeing it yes
and simply by dwelling on that he became
a fully enlightened Buddha but not by
actually seeing it with no his eyes and
looking at it so he seemed so it's
metaphorically sorry so yeah so he
understands that say he understand exist
he dwells
he remains he says spends time
understanding hmm
you not only has has the aggregates each
aggregate has manifested
but this is there's a rising this is
like increasing in its presence hmm or
it's decreasing their presence
either way it's manifested yeah so such
as matter such as the arising a matter
so in other words say in regards to
sights something you see something that
may be affecting you either with passion
or a version say a displeasing sight
yeah that you really really want done by
yeah if you keep observing that you will
remain ignorant of the nature of singing
because you're fully absorbed with the
object off of your sight which is where
the site is but the point is you
understand the arising and ceasing what
I want to call it off the eye which is a
necessary basis for any type of sight
pleasing or displeasing and you can't
see the eye on the level of sight yeah
so you get to see the truth of the eye
yes but not by the physical actual scene
because that's secondary thing but back
onto that Polly that's right
so the same that fit but a bodhisattva
path see when he talks about rising
force he's the simple no he's talking
about a abaya dead so rise and fall
that's the rise and fall that's when we
discussed before in terms of increasing
and decreasing exactly and there's also
well no actually that's slightly
different that there's another way it's
talked about which is it's a powder
powder and via similar yeah so but those
though that's that's what we've talked
about the the three characteristics
rising is manifest
disappearing or passing permanent
falling his manifest rising and falling
let's say rising is manifesting decrease
either way something indoors and this
change yeah he's changing one way or the
other so so that's or die by or harder
by but that's not what's in this suit
over there died yeah it's different it's
completely different it's them
this butcher and Nick would you and that
appears quite a lot in the suitors in
the stock phrase when usually I think
it's a householder here's the number and
says it's like it's as if an upright
what was upside down what was first to
protect them I was taking for food
that's something slightly different
that's different views yeah so this this
specific balance upside down this what
was up what was our down on there down
it's not right Nick Mooji town look
would you go Jay a good punch one turns
up what was down down yeah so it is
exactly the wrong order
yeah so I've got it
so this is this is this is ood ie saying
how amazing how much work he's done in
in so far as he has
pondered over turning around turning up
prior to the upside down nurse if the
father seemed ever gets hmm yeah it's
actually even probably because usually I
would probably refer to those examples
of people people here the good and there
now it's like they're turning upside
down put in first a second but then
people can sometimes dismiss that yes I
know what is just like they were related
so that's why I would Express yeah no
it's an accurate why would you express
it in accurately even if you're related
I kind of accurate understanding exactly
the whole point yeah you actually
understood now but now you're gonna in
accurately describe it but anyway this
is even more pertaining to he's actually
contemplating the right order of things
yeah so what is the wrong order or the
father student ID aggregates from the
point of view of your personal
experience what would constitute the
wrong order I come first
so this matter is mine I was in me or
it's you first and that's the point that
self-centeredness of it so if you
understand it doesn't matter how
self-centered your sense of self might
feel high in control how much present it
is its present within its second to them
it's dependent on them it's not so
literal is the same thing that remains
there you're just instead of placing like this
don't create new things you don't
introduce new components into the farm
aggregates when you start practicing the
down be impossible but but the whole
emotional significance of well
everything because the whole samsara
depends on the wrong road it's not
that's I mean like some sorry is not
outside or something a universe of
rebirths where you just travel through
no it's within your point of view that's
what your point of view is samsara is
the wrong views I'm sorry is that the
structure there on board
for as long as that's there you keep
reappearing you keep enduring but by
contemplating turning that round hmm one
can discern oh well yeah I mean that
that's how it was expressed there well
you can pretty much discern anything
that was teaching about it cuz it's the
principle it's no bother ya with this
this is with this first this is second
as in this description of the wrong
order yeah now without this is first
have had a second is the description the
right order so with the grain against
the grain all those things that were
used to describe it so bad and that's
really so this and again even in
petitioners experience there is petits
Impala there is sense of I am and
everything else that belongs to me that
I can use act see here taste touch think
about and so on but it's the potato
butter with the grain you go with the
grain of ignorance yeah knee towards the
world so it's still me in the world if
you want to call it like that
but then you realize the world as in
this body material all the senses eat
the container yeah it's a necessary
basis yeah for the existence of my
notion of self so I'm not denying my
nose yourself I'm just not seeing it as
mine anymore because it doesn't depend
on me wanting to keep it but it depends
on these things allowing it to be but
it's all the same thing me and the
matter me in the world but now it's a
position it's all this is the first
actually this is the second not this is
the first and that's the second
so that's what it but it's so bad at the
its principle is described as with this
this is yeah with this this is with this
this is yeah without this this won't be
yeah so if this is not first this cannot
be the second
and contemplating the right order it's
probably something that Regina can do
well that's what I think what's going on
here he he's he's describing himself as
a patoot you know pondering over turning
around it's almost as if what if I were
to turn around
whoa don't what what if I were to out of
near faith in the yeah and he's teaching
how the love for him every god this is
first and this is sec yeah I've it
doesn't seem natural today he contradict
it goes against the grain of my
experience yeah there's nothing that
I've got there's no validation immediate
that it's true that's right but what if
I were to do it out of me at faith and
that's exactly the faith type in the
students this is Scott people think
faith that means you're just purely
devoted infatuated and somehow you
become another an economy unsaturation
yeah no means did you start applying the
dumb upon a kind of faith nothing else
like somebody else would need to make
some sense why would the right order
work and based on getting some
intellectual understanding why that
order would work he gets to apply the
right order and because it is a right
order it would work and the result of it
the verification of it working is being
free from suffering of midst of
suffering we can't suffer you're
incapable of suffering oh yeah we worked
but somebody who doesn't necessarily
ponder on it can't make sense of it
could just do it because they understood
to the extent that that's what they
would appoint yeah so that's why even
the faith that even him over there cuz
was clearly faith that yes he said it's
all but it was just inspired like he had
no relation to the Sun or nothing
basically it was just inspired with and
that's what he became a monk even he was
then you know the fact that he was able
to at least get the notion of oh maybe I
should put this first at this second
means this he had some grasp some
instruction that he made sense of yeah
that's the difference between a suit or
putana and suit up Virginia I don't
think I don't think I think it actually
says the suit of a bhikkhu in the suitors but
the suit of a bhikkhu in the suitors but
don't think you ever actually see six of
a patoot you're not right right you just
see how she's always yeah but then you
can infer there is someone who's had
some instruction doesn't see it for
themselves yeah but see so now that the to Jenna
yeah but see so now that the to Jenna
who understood the right order at least
got the notion of it
can start to apply to an account of the
faith in the willow
yes she thinks the food is the greatest
you just do what everybody says or if he
doesn't have such faith he can then
start applying it after pondering on it
yeah he thinks about it and what
actually makes more sense yeah
what if I were to try to do this and
sustain this and cultivate this and
develop this by the way that person
would arrive at the right view doesn't
matter where you came to faith or
through investigation the point is to
write
so the first what would be the necessary
condition for for a petitioner to be
able to start practicing that I order
except understanding that there is such
thing as right order but what what he
needs to do in order to understand it
sorry what so conclusion yeah
we're solution of the teaching these
heads per second and inaudible in the
water in order to start pondering on the
right order
as his his dad knew that I did what does
he must stop doing okay he first of all
practice restraint and stop ratifying
his yes secondly don't keep so keep
precepts Frank's restraint and spent on
his own yeah that's on that level of the
lifestyle yeah but would be the second
thing it's kind of more eternal what
would he have to stop doing so as we
described the order is the sense of self
and and the in everything else
yeah but the rather world is everything
else and the sense of self so he needs
to stop including everything else you
need to stand in good but above all he
needs to stop either ignoring the center
so it's trying to get rid of because
that's practically speaking what most
people who got the notion of the
Buddhist teaching be doing yeah there is
no self there is no self and obviously
everything serves to like override the
sense of self is doing he's not saying
all is just changing the priority how
can you change the approach to do things
if you keep denying no it's not real the
scent is very it's very real
yeah but it's not first yeah it's the
second exactly so he spent his time just
recognizing the self that has manifested
right here in the way in the kind of
well I yeah whatever yeah whatever
whatever big you sense I might be if I
try to overly define it I do have a
sense of self I am such as such yeah a
certain individual something they were
there this like a group of
characteristics so to speak they do kind
of outline the phenomenon of I am yeah
well I might be different or whatever
but there is the sense of I am the
reason why people struggle with it is
cuz they always depend on like overly
defining yet in order for it to be clear
real that's not a thing and
let's exam in clarify I can put my
finger on it
well no see the direction of putting
your finger on it even if there's
nothing to put a finger on it
it's really sad yeah yeah so you lose oh
so you can put the finger on the
direction where you will be putting a
finger but you are unaware of it cuz you
only want to put your finger that's real
if you basically your attempts to
clarify something neat that's something
to be bad yeah well yeah so it to me the
sense of self you can't make it more
specific than that yeah but then you
also must stop the night
oh there's no sense of everything cuz I
know who I love told me that and that's
I think the main work we'll put organize
that learning how to discern the
ambiguity of the sense of self without
overly defining it and without ignoring
it so learning phenomenon and then
yourself yeah yeah changing the other
thing is sort of its employers yeah
because now you know that there is this
phenomenon enduring regardless of what
you think about it regardless whether
you acted you denied there's a sense of
I you know so within the sense of I am
you discerned the sense of everything
else that belongs to that I am and then
you see that everything else that
belongs to him is the reason the tensor
I am is there it's not hard way around
but at that time you have grasped
assigned of your mind thoroughly and
then you could so it's not like fixing
the order like 1 & 2 yes it's more like
hard to put it like a long-sleeve shirt
it's inside out
so it's really turning it back the right
way so you have to go literally through
the sleeve and pull it out okay you have
to go through the center self yeah you
have to go through the center self to
them pull out that rider all that and
but Santa's are still there but now that
which was belonging to send yourself
it's actually the reason for the sense
of self and the reason why it's not one
in two is because you are it so you
can't step outside and see the sense of
self relating to this and that then your
point of view is where the sense of self
is so first you need to allow that
phenomenal center self to endure and
then see through it and by doing so
eventually they tend to self that still
in use is now seen a second so it's all
knife to will enact to fix your after or
even even I mean that's a nice example
but you can't you can't imagine you
going in and pulling the thing yeah well
you imagine yourself being in the Slayer
exactly so the inside of the slave
should be outside yeah but you're inside
so it's like I coming outside anyway
if you succeed to pull it out then you
realize that now the order is right and
you will know the order is right because
you will be untouchable at you by the
suffering so you're not hiding from
suffering you're not denying it you're
not afraid of it yeah and he cannot
touch you you've understood the essence
of suffering this is America so it's the
most direct verification you can have
yeah then goes on to say one say the
demo was broken through to by me you
know I broke through to the demo the
path was obtained by me which when
developed by me made much of dwelling in
this way will bring me to the truth so
that I will understand birth this
destroy there's no more of this so the
sense of the right order did he
establish if you just cultivated
protected maintain it the complete this
passion will have to be the result of it
and and you know that I said he knows if
he just keeps doing this oh yeah there's
no doubt about it
exactly now you see the end the result
of this and that's the toy sort of one
understands what is he see there
no that's the ending of this yeah he
cannot result in anything else yeah
so that's what the developing
satipatthana the right view is the one way always
the right view is the one way always
just arrived only one direction that can
result in
and what's the common translation of
that passage which what the one you read
just a last bit about the inside up
turning the something like having
confidentiy twirling I mean the key
phrase yeah so so so be something like
yeah examining the surge and decline
right so the commentary the bit you read
is identifying that the wrong order
right order parley with the arising at
the golden wire of the other party them
sound like that's right that's right
yeah because they couldn't understand
what is disorder me
so that's that's already a red flag
another thing one thing is to ponder
what it means of trying to understand
the context or something that being said
but another thing is like Polly says one
thing you can't make sense out of it so
then you're just assumed that or it's
the same like that other time when a
different Polly said something different
yeah yeah the reason is like well you
might not even if I just understand
what's being said yeah so even if you
get it right it would be for the wrong
reason and you know you were well at
least closer to the clear understanding
of it is when you develop a context they
would include both yeah they would not
need changing yeah exactly
like we explained now it can be
explained like the way we explained it
before yeah arising intensifying and
increasing and decreasing of the same
thing that in doers that's why they send
the order so we explain two different
messages to different parties two
different descriptions with the same
context yeah so without and they're no
loose ends there so it's like it's like
the words son Karan hmm so that seems to
be I think this common view seems that
there's different different usages of
the word so it can it can mean yeah I
think conditions for the things or it
can mean things that are compounded yeah
or it can be completely sure that means
you don't work if you exactly if you've
got all these completely different ideas
I think people don't necessarily realize
or appreciate for that matter is deer
like the Buddha Gautama was the foremost
that means the most accurate exactly
that doesn't mean the form was the most
poetic inspirational
speaker the orator no means the most
accurate in describing and expounding
and teaching the Dharma so if he did not
choose a different term yeah means it's
not a different thing yeah exactly
sometimes oh well you think wasn't clear
and he used this world like this and
they were like yeah most people would
probably do that except Buddha Gautama
who was the foremost bounding the Dhamma
exactly so if he was using the world for
some Sankara in all these different
contexts means you now you need to
understand the context all of it it's
not try to tailor the word to mean
different things in different contexts
that's just tying off the loose ends why
would you patching it matching this
Dhamma free from patchwork and networks
and car is the most fundamental
principle of a 2-part yeah to single can
use things yeah that's what's encouraged
yeah if you understand that every single
context every single instance
exemplification that's a car will fall
into that principle and there is no need
for patchwork cuz it's all included
and that that should be the criteria
again even for petitioner who starts to
get the notion of the Buddhist teaching
you must find the context they will not
contradict itself they will not need
changing of the meaning of the term like
you understood the context of Sankara oh
but now you came across the different
meaning of Sankara and your context
falls apart that's not the context that
yeah but instead of now refusing to let
go of that context that you've got some
sense of it and then trying to no this
is probably what it means and that meant
that and this meant they so just that
you can allow yourself to have a
contradictory context based on Sankara
that doesn't always mean that which you
thought it means you should really
abandon your context and keep doing the
work it's more unpleasant but it's it's
exactly what a practice that you have to
admit I actually don't know what the
context is being described exactly so
the context that was limited which means
it's only the best probably the best
example of that was the Nibbana is that
in my mind you Monica thinking 30 36 but
there was that bit with the good of
describes somebody with a sense of I am
attaining the Nibbana and he says oh
this is Nibbana I am you Nibbana listen
about his mind
mm-hmm and then he was like oh how can
you you know because for most people
Nibbana is this notion of you know like
a mystical experience if you're unaware
of yourself you just surrendered to the
universe kind of thing yeah so how can
you with your self-awareness with your
sense of I am experience new modern
auras and we had this discussion like
with random
monks and laypeople few many years ago
and so this this passage was brought up
and any people like you know and then
some other people saying well no it's
probably it's not the real Nibbana
and then they said look remember that
suitable with the Buddha's that man
what is Nibbana for you and he said this
this is all Disney banana that's hitting
his limbs this health health is not any
burner and we said that's ridiculous and
then pointed out why that's wrong yeah
so then this audience probably means
refers to that Romney Barna Buddha was
saying that it was in the vendor man had
the right of you yeah and I was like
yeah no that's probably cuz it was the
real me bar you know the mystical
experience of Nirvana and then this must
be the wrong Nibbana yes it has quite
surprised they are saying that because
in the same suiter continues and says
this man is describing about the man who
says I'm in the banner
Nibbana is mine he factually asserts
that which Nibbana is so I read that out
loud and he was just silent just know so
and that's the perfect example of that
completely limited donk context yeah you
have an idea of what Nibbana is and here
you are in the same suit from the same
person the buddha himself he said not
that did that man also describe the bar
and it doesn't fit with your end the ban
is undescribable yeah but the Buddha
said this man with the wrong view
describes that which me bana is but he
doesn't obtain it cuz she still
prioritizes his sense of self and you
couldn't make sense out of it so you
have two options either you ignore did
you just contradicted the Buddha yeah oh
you realize that exactly automatically
that's what it's implied which is why
you would choose to contradict or
pretend you didn't hear it yeah it was
like a when I read it out loud it was
just like silence and then anyway in
discussion just like like you never
happen
alternatively you realize oh no that I
cannot tolerate that I should not
tolerate that contradiction so I must
now undo the context of what I thought
Nibbana and my goal and my 20 years of
practice were leading to and I've read
that we'll be able to include this which
means I need to clarify even what I
thought I understood which I haven't
yeah not protected blindly against
anything they might challenge it then
goes the same by the way in Murupara
so ya can see if the Nevada conceives in
the bomb techs Nevada oh this must be do
it's really bana it's a really moment so
by all means conceive Nibbana is yours
means you've done much more work than if
you just conceived sensuality as yours
but fundamentally yes conceiving is
still there which means the wrong order
is still there which means what this man
understood the right order hasn't been
understood and that's like the example
how can somebody become enlightened
almost in an instant is because they've
done all the work of replacing any
inferior conceiving with the conceiving
of Nibbana conceiving of dispassion
disenchantment letting go and imagine
you've done all that work already and
all you need to do now you see that is
first and your sense of self a second
that's it that's all that's left and
there is no no that's why they became
out of hands just the Buddha said one
sentence minds were alight cuz they done
all the work of fixing the right order
and now just understanding it as such
and again as we mentioned before the
body suit people think he was just lucky
that the Buddha told me that in the
scene there will just be the scene and
they know the fact that he was a quite
austere back wearing ascetic who knows
hollow decades maybe off extremely
enunciation and commitment and he
genuinely thought he was enlightened
cause it's absolutely perfect this
passion nothing nothing can affect him
and when he okay that was the missing
bit that's it I mean all he needed was
uh turrents of another he already
developed the only so I'm gonna say
Carol thoroughly yeah the two factors
for the right view say had he hadn't
thought to change the order and you
cannot think that we don't external
instruction but you do you would be some
somebody to be had to come to work in
the value of this passion the restraint
all of that all of that is fully
understood and that's what we meant by
some beings
have little dust in their eyes means the
pollutions have been either undone or
haven't been developed or or the effort
has been made and you know they've been
abandoned like his previous teachers
that he want to go and teach not out of
gratitude or some devotional respect but
simply because it's the least work for
him so no who should I teach first although
so no who should I teach first although
those beings that need very little
teaching why don't I start with them
yeah so the other butter just ends that
Souter I mean he's getting here then
goes through and talks about the various
factors of awakening they've been
obtained by him that's why I think it's
what he's saying is looking and
amazingly so how much has been done by
me yes people might think that sounds
conceited it's just do you sound
conceited but it's just affect your
States based on AB and abandonment of
the conceit and that's that's why it's
so amazing you know they were never did
in the pseudonym are easily marvelous
isn't it isn't it wonderful
did I can glide the Sun blinds things
like that that's extreme you can see
it's just you would amazed by use by
yourself cuz it's not based on your
conceit it's not based on I am and then
and then the Buddha responses says good
good would I this path will die has
indeed been obtained by you which when
developed by you know child welling in
this way will bring you to the truth so
that you will understand birth is
destroyed